[Music]
hey folks welcome to the Dark Horse
podcast livestream our 15th livestream
I'm sitting with dr. Heather hi and we
are we are prepared to have quite an
interesting discussion today I must say
that some of the topics we are going to
cover I regard as a bit dire and I'm
hoping that there will be some humor in
here but I should just prepare people at
home that if there is humor it is likely
to be gallows humor
how are you feeling oh yeah pretty much
the same pretty much the same okay good
I'm glad we're on the same page yes
that's always a good thing yes for
newcomers let's alert them to the
structure of things we will do about an
hour of conversation on some topics that
we have decided to discuss you can file
super chat questions on YouTube and we
will do our best to answer them we will
start with two questions from Twitter
and then we will answer as many Supercat
questions as possible in the second hour
anything else announcement wise all
right excellent
so I believe we're going to start today
with a discussion of the question not of
whether or not this virus has emerged
from the lab but a question that often
comes up in response to discussions of
that topic and the question that I see
variations of is what difference would
it make
so it's come from a lab so it hasn't
come from a lab we still have to do the
same things and which is true at a first
approximation with regard to some of the
actions that we might take yes some of
them are certainly absolutely universal
and it makes no difference but I must
say I am increasingly alarmed by the
possibility that a laboratory origin
would actually suggest something
radically different about this virus and
might explain some of the anomalous
features that we see and might have a
lot to say about what
a course of action going forward would
look like so maybe we choose should just
flag this and say that I think it was
episode 10 where you in particular
talked about a lot of what you saw as
some of the emerging evidence that this
was this did emerge from a lab not as a
bio weapon likely but as part of normal
ongoing research in the last livestream
that would be number 14 you showed a
flowchart that you had made with your
estimates as the likelihood of the
various origins and it's likely that in
a future episode I don't know if it's a
live stream or not that you may continue
this cover as well but you have plans to
potentially continue this conversation
so you are not evading this particular
part of it it's just not the focus of
what we're doing right now right now I
think it's very important that we talk
about the nature of that evidence and I
do want to get into it but I think for
people there are a couple of things that
you should note about the public
discussion that would tell you why we're
so focused on this one is the people who
dismiss what we've done on the podcast
almost invariably call it a conspiracy
theory we have been very careful to
point out that this is a hypothesis and
that a hypothesis is actually a unknown
quantity we understand how a hypothesis
functions how you would know if it was
true and when something is offered as a
hypothesis it doesn't even mean that the
person offering it is a believer that it
is correct it is a formalization of a
possibility and it suggests mechanisms
whereby you might establish or falsify
its validity so we've been careful about
that and our detractors have tried to
push us into this conspiracy theory buzz
saw and I would just say I don't think
it's worth taking seriously anybody who
uses the term conspiracy theory to deal
with a legitimate hypothesis as we've
said earlier here if we try to assess
our world through the lens of Occam's
razor
also known as the law of parsimony which
suggests that all else being equal the
simplest explanation is most likely to
be the true explanation then it seems
like an easy thing for those who suggest
conspiracy to be debunked but that's not
true just because you were trying
to see to understand the world with the
lens of Occam's razor does not mean the
conspiracy does not happen it just means
that it shouldn't be your default
assumption right and you know on the
flowchart that I presented there's a
pathway whereby this virus emerged as an
intentional release it has a very low
probability on it I don't think that
this is likely to be true there's no
evidence for it so far but on the formal
list of all the possibilities it has to
be there okay but let's talk about what
you and we think the evolutionary
implications of what this virus is doing
and might come to do our if it was at
least partially engineered likely to be
a hybridized recombinant virus in a lab
from two pre-existing extent viruses out
there in the world presumably in a bat
and a penguin well I want to say one
more thing about that the public
discussion which is the most alarming
thing about the public discussion is
that there is almost no dissenting
opinion to be found amongst
establishment virologists as to whether
or not this could have come from a lab
and this is alarming because when one
looks at the evidence it's not that it
is clear that it came from a lab but it
is clear that it might have come from a
lab and that would explain at least the
major coincidence of where on earth it
emerged so the absence of that
discussion forces those of us who are
not establishment biologists to take up
the slack and to have this discussion
and really I feel it as a kind of
obligation if they were discussing this
and I saw something that looked like a
rational discussion I might be
interested in entering that discussion
sometimes based on evolutionary things
that they might be missing but it's
perfectly possible that we wouldn't have
to do this but in the absence of that
responsible discussion at the highest
levels of virology somehow we've got to
do this in podcast world which is far
from ideal sure all right so let's talk
about the question of not if it came
from a lab but what if it came from a
lab what would that suggest about where
we are
the thing that is increasingly alarming
me and maybe I should remind people that
if I have a scientific claim to fame it
is in the study of telomeres senescence
and cancer I advanced a hypothetical
model which now has considerable support
that aging is the downside that comes
with a protective mechanism against
cancers based in telomeres things at the
ends of chromosomes in order to do that
work I had to go through a roadblock
which was that mice did not appear
consistent with that hypothesis because
they had extremely long telomeres and
short lives and what I ended up
hypothesizing which was later
demonstrated in a lab by Carol Greider
and Mike Eamonn was that mice don't
actually have long telomeres that this
was the result of evolution inside a
laboratory environment that nobody had
thought to worry about because they
didn't realize that they had created
artificial selection of a very intense
type may i reword this in a sentence the
observation that mice have long
telomeres was not itself untrue
except that mice weren't mice its lab
mice mice that have been bred in and for
in laboratories for laboratory research
have long telomeres but wild mice do not
therefore it was the category mouse that
was an error and most people who weren't
organism by ologists evolutionary
biologists don't think that deeply about
what it means when you say Mouse you
know that it's many many species or that
it might be different depending on
population even but that that is the
distinction it's not that the initial
observation of long telomeres in
parentheses some mice wasn't true but
that there was a erroneous over
generalization of the observation in
these lab created and now lab studied
mice to suggest that it was all mice
that's perfectly said so one of the
outgrowth of this is the recognition
that evolution in a laboratory
environment can in fact be extremely
rapid and has important consequences for
the creatures that are the result of it
all right so now back to the question of
well what if this did emerge in a lab
one of the things you have to understand
about the laboratory work that
urologists regularly deploy in the study
of things like coronaviruses is that
they use a kind of serial passage which
is a technical term for infecting
something be it cells or living animals
with a virus either a natural virus or
one that they've created as a chimera
and then allowing it to be transmitted
one cell to the next or one animal to
the next and that this uses an
experimental process to determine both
what the nature of the virus is when it
is exposed to tissues that allow it to
function and also it allows us to see
something about the evolutionary
trajectory of viruses over time now the
question is it is clear I believe we're
almost clear that this is initially a
bat virus that we're dealing with at the
Maine bat bat bat bat virus probably
from horseshoe that's almost certainly
from horseshoe bats but did the
progenitor virus either the actual virus
or certainly the progenitor virus came
from a species of horseshoe bat that
doesn't live right around Wuhan Daluz
within a few hundred miles yeah and we
always have to leave open the
possibility that there could be some
other creature with a better match but
from what we know of coronaviruses in
creatures and we know a fair amount it
does look like the core of the virus we
are dealing with does come from a bat
recently how recently and by what
mechanism that's what the dispute is
about but if this virus was taken into a
lab and then escaped just by incorrect
handling let's say but without
modification then this probably says
very little about what we're facing
because we're dealing with a virus that
could have jumped to somebody in a cave
and it would have the characteristics
that the ancestral virus has on the
other hand if somebody composited
several viruses in order probably to
study the danger of viruses that might
emerge from a cave if they took a virus
and they turbocharged it to
it especially infectious in order that
they could study the process of
infection maybe generate a therapy or a
vaccine then they would have imbued it
with characteristics that might actually
be very difficult for a natural virus to
have come by there are mechanisms but
they require as we've talked about
previously they would require for
example two viruses from two different
sources to infect the same animal to
find themselves in the same cell and
then to engage in a kind of
recombination which is not impossible
but it's difficult so that's a very
unlikely thing it may happen but that's
very different than somebody in a lab
deciding to take characteristics from
here and characteristics from there and
fuse them together and make what-if
amounts to a super virus but even worse
is the fact that if somebody took such a
super virus and then they went through
one of these serial passage experiments
they a would have I believe selected for
adaptation to the laboratory environment
itself and B they might have induced a
tendency in the virus to experiment
beyond what a normal virus would do let
me just pause this for a moment and say
I don't think you even need all of that
precursor argument about if they made a
super virus that that would render the
further selection in the lab through
serial passage experimentation more
likely to produce a particularly
horrifying virus but even absent that
absent the production of super virus all
you really need is serial passage
experimentation on a recombinant virus
that's in the lab that's experimenting
iterations of generations in the lab and
you have a situation in which selection
as you are about to get to selection is
likely to produce a virus that explores
rapidly and with very few breaks so I
think I feel like the bit about if the
lab had created this super bug we don't
need that and that actually produces
more that's that's a big potential break
in this logical chain that we don't need
to make the rest of the argument yeah I
believe what you've just said is
accurate
um the the compositing of two viruses is
unnecessary to the necessity of us
figuring out whether this came from a
lab through serial passage because but
I'm not even objecting to the idea that
it was compositing of two viruses I mean
it's you know this pang possible Hangul
and Spike protein on sort of a virus
body that's from a horseshoe bat doesn't
need to have been done in pursuit of
super bugs so that's that's specifically
the language that I'm Jack and you know
that's the thing it's gonna be easy to
dismiss that you can you know that you
can imagine that you that you or we know
something about what was in the hearts
and minds of the researchers who are
producing such a thing even if it's a
composite it doesn't necessarily have to
have been a composite with a particular
goal especially in a various goal so I
just I just want us to be very careful
here that I feel like the the
interesting thing that we can add that
is that is new that is that is novel is
the evolutionary analysis of what the
labid what a virus that experienced
strong selection in the lab might do
once it then escapes into the world like
that is the new thing that we haven't
quite gotten to yet and I think it makes
no sense to potentially give ammunition
to the would be discredited by making an
argument about production of superbugs
at the lab we don't know maybe but
that's actually not necessary for the
rest of the argument I agree it's not
necessary we do know a lot about what
was in the minds of the people studying
these viruses because they published
effectively you know may not be a
perfectly accurate or complete rendering
of their thought process because they
were publishing along the way we know a
lot about what we were thinking what
they were thinking and why they you know
we're inclined to do the research but
anyway I agree with you totally
unnecessary the serial passage in and of
itself will have had a selective effect
on the viruses how extreme in effect in
other words was there enough time for it
to change the viruses that is uncertain
however so why don't you just say a
little bit about what you think the
Selective effect of just simply serial
passage experimentation on viruses or
commented or not in the lab might have
before we get to then what happens when
viruses release well let's start with
another system and non virus so you can
see the the basic parameters I remember
from long ago when we were actually
undergraduates at UCSC I took a great
course with Bob Traverse it was a
seminar Bob Trivers led it and Austin
burt was a postdoc at the time
Austin Burk is a very important
evolutionary biologist trevor's is one
of the greats and anyway the the issue
of chimerism in cattle came up Austin
brought it up and you need a little bit
of technical terminology here to
understand this but it's not tough when
a mammal it's true for other creatures
but when a mammal creates a sex cell and
egg or sperm chimerism or Kia's about
frequency chiasma feet oh we really need
to go back and clarify because there are
two very different terms that mean
different things not really because it's
a chimeric chromosome but anyway you're
right chiasma is the the right term so
when a cell reproduces to make sex cells
either eggs or sperm the chromosomes
that the creature that's making those
cells got from its mother and its father
actually the two chromosomes that carry
similar information line up together
many of you will remember this from your
high school biology class they line up
together at the equator of the cell and
then they swap information so that the
sperm carries Composites and the egg
carries Composites of the mother the
maternal and paternal chromosomes but it
doesn't carry the originals right it
carries they've been shuffled and the
question of how so these shuffling
events are called chiasma right so
chiasma frequency is how much shuffling
went on between the father's and
mother's chromosomes to make the ones
that go into the sperm or the egg
the chiasma frequency is itself subject
to evolutionary pressure and the point
that austin put in front of us was that
in cattle in particular the Chi a
domestic domestic wild cattle but
domestic cattle
I think cattle means domestic but anyway
it doesn't matter
but this but this the paper which
unfortunately we could not find
yesterday when we were looking for it
suggested specifically that it wasn't in
wild buffets but only in domestic cattle
yeah have an incredibly high chiasma
frequency and the interpretation was
that when we exert artificial selection
in you know in the feedlot we are
looking for characteristics that serve
us that may not come together they may
be you know maybe that the large animal
has a low tendency to produce milk or is
resistant to producing milk when it
doesn't have a suckling calf or
something like this and so in selecting
four components that we want together in
one animal we inadvertently without you
know long before genes were even
understood we were selecting for high
rates of shuffling in these animals so
that an animal that is highly
experimental tends to leave offspring
because it brings together combinations
of characteristics that are desirable
from the point of view of the farmer or
whatever and what it means in part for
genome to be highly experimental to use
your language is to have a high rate of
chiasma yes that's one of the ways that
you can introduce novel combinations
that would be desirable and so in effect
strains of cattle would appeal to those
who decide whether they reproduce or
fail to reproduce by producing
combinations that are novel and
sometimes contain something that's very
desirable to a dairy farmer website well
the same thing will be true of a corona
virus being passed from one cell to
another in the lab in the sense that
whatever the environment of the lab
might be then the cells that
successfully pass under those conditions
will be the ones that are in the you
know if you go ten passages before you
then look to see which descendants of
the initial virus are present they will
be the ones that succeeded under those
conditions and unless the lab is
specifically looking for stability in a
viral genome or viral phenotype then it
will be exactly looking for change and
therefore be selecting inadvertently in
all likelihood be possibly advertently
for four
rates of change right asthma so if you
accept that logic so far then the result
of it is that what we may be facing if
this is an escapee from a lab and the
lab was engaged in these kinds of
experiments then what we may be facing
is a virus that is more exploratory than
a bat virus that infected somebody
walking through a cave would have been
because although that virus would still
have a need to discover new ways of
being and you know in general these
things go extinct pretty quickly they do
sometimes jump to people which the
jangly lab has demonstrated but in
general those infections don't spread to
the globe so if we created a virus that
was adapted to laboratory conditions
that would have potentially some
positive effects for us that would
probably be temporary and it would have
some negative effects the negative
effect would be wow maybe we've created
something highly experimental and that
might just be able to spread across the
globe to different populations to
different regions to different climates
very very rapidly and which of course is
exactly what we see two different organs
and a different organs so not just
across space globally but across space
and system within individuals so this is
actually why this topic has got me in
kind of a dark mode because to the
extent that this virus is teaching us
how it behaves it seems to be quite
anomalous the list of symptoms seems to
grow by the week if not by the day the
number of different syndromes that we
see I mean it's it's even notable that
we are calling this SARS because that
was the first thing it looked like but
from the point of view of all of the
other things it creates you know this is
not inherently respiratory that is it
seems to be the way into the body in
general but but it seems cardiac it's
neurological it's blood it's children
it's old people it manifests differently
and well not just in different ages and
different demographics but in different
populations which may be an indication
of
very different strains circulating
simultaneously which we'll get to a
little bit later yeah so if this is the
cat it also on the plus side and this is
a hypothesis I don't even know if I
believe it but I know that it is worthy
of consideration yes it is possible that
the and we will get back to why we think
this is the case but it is possible that
the difficulty that one has contracting
this disease outdoors that is to say the
rarity with which it appears to be
transmitted by people in an outdoor
environment is the result of the fact
that effectively the laboratory selected
for viruses that are very good at being
transmitted in an indoor environment and
if that is the case then I believe it
suggests that we have a limited amount
of time to exploit its inability to jump
from one person to the next
outdoors wellness I think you've said in
an earlier live stream this would be the
case if it had a immediate precursor bat
origin as well aware transmission was
likely happening between bats and a cave
or we've got serial passage
experimentation of a possibly
recombinant virus in a laboratory either
way you've got close quarters and no UV
light and add add sunlight add air
increase decrease population density
increase space between would be carriers
would be transmitters and the thing
seems to have a very much harder time
getting between hosts yeah and it's
actually it's amazing how extreme this
effect is so one of the things you and I
have talked about this there are certain
things that are very hard to render
graphically so all biologists of our age
I would say suffer from a bad model of
the way neurons function for example
because a neuron in the brain might be
connected its dendrites might be
connected to a thousand other neurons
it's very hard to depict that in any way
that looks other than like a hairy cell
right it's very hard to
to depict abiotic computer in which each
of the things that seem like wires are
actually computers unto themselves
connected to a thousand other cells at a
time and so we have a bad sense of what
a neuron is and how complex the
interaction of one neuron what the next
might be likewise we have a bad model
for how viruses are transmitted the fact
that I mean and this is not new this
virus appears highly sensitive to the
quantity of virus that one encounters
right that does not fit the cartoons
that we've now all seen with a virus
reaching a cell and gaining entry now
that those cartoons are true right as
far as we know a virus enters a cell and
coaxes the cell into doing its bidding
but but no no cartoon is going to convey
the importance of viral load and time so
the character single-frame cartoons
can't do a good job of conveying that or
if they do they can't they won't also
convey the you know what you just
suggested that the typical image does I
mean this this does also point out to
the problem you know the problem with
science education the problem with
textbooks the you know the reason that
textbooks textbooks tend to have these
really simple cartoons even at the
highest levels even a high level neuro
textbooks and immunology textbooks right
is that language isn't the only way that
we taking information and having
information come in and you know across
multiple domains not just say
linguistically but also visually also
auditorally can really help synthesize
and gain more understanding in the brain
but it's also really easy for those
oversimplified visuals in particular or
sound bytes right anything but is simple
that you can remember without really
having to force it through the first
principles analysis is going to be going
to be likely to pop out and then confuse
people into thinking oh that's that's
the truth that's you know science says
therefore that's the truth
yeah the problem is they especially as
you point out the visual stuff takes on
a reality of its own then
cryptically informs people or
misinformed them and you'll all be able
to detect this in yourselves if you
think about a diagram of the solar
system when we were at Evergreen I
always wanted to get a little grant to
install a scale model of the solar
system because the solar system isn't
anything like the diagrams in a textbook
because you can't do it you know if the
Sun either you know if the Sun is yay
big and the earth is tiny and then Pluto
is a long walk right how do you depict
that on a page right and it would on
that campus it would have been possible
because it was on a thousand acres of
forest whereas most places can't even
imagine having such a model and most
many many observatories try this and you
know you'll run into a planet somewhere
in some totally different room where the
center of the Sun was far away but of
course the walls are their exhibits
between it it it doesn't really make the
point as strongly you really need to
walk to Pluto before you understand but
wait this is just for me now no no okay
believe me I need you right there but so
anyway we've departed from the topic but
I'm not even convinced that we
understand by we I mean the scientific
establishment understands why viral load
plays the role it does in infection and
you know maybe it does maybe we just
don't know but but there's something
there's some system that is dealing with
a large number of things a large number
of incoming viral particles successfully
in general but too many viral particles
at once or in a short period of time
overwhelms it could be the you know the
macrophages and other general generalist
cells are really successful at capturing
free-floating virus that they don't have
particular warnings about but that they
can all be occupied and something gets
over the wall who knows but in any case
the the laboratory environment would in
all probability have favored certain
characteristics and to the extent
that Subway's local trains seems
something like a cage in which you might
have a bunch of animals who you were
trying to infect in order to see what
the consequence was for them and what
the result was for the virus nursing
homes meatpacking plants yeah exactly
so you know could this be a dead end and
and irrelevant it could be but if it
isn't a dead end I can't escape the idea
that this is really at some level
possibly the most important question in
the world at the moment is to the extent
that we can get a leg up on this virus
by finding out what we know of its
nature if it came from a lab the people
who ran that lab know things that we
need to know and I'm not suggesting I
think people try to push ideas to the
near the nearest idea that they know
themselves and they synonymous the - we
know that Thinking Fast and Slow would
be a good place to hear about this kind
of cognitive bias but in any case I'm
not advocating I'm not even interested
in responsibility if these were
scientists working honorably what I'm
really interested in is what might they
know about what we're up against if this
if this thing has been selected for a
laboratory environment and one of the
things that it that imbued it with was a
low resistance to UV light because it
borrowed capacity from resistance to UV
light in order to do other things that
made a difference in the lab if having
it the hypothesis being it would have
been able to borrow capacity for
resistance to UV light because it was
experiencing novi UV light and therefore
it suffered nothing in the immediate
environment which was being selected for
rise to spell out the argument there
would be a trade-off and this would be a
cheap place to borrow yeah well if
that's true then what we would expect is
over time as this thing floats around in
the world it will evolve a resistance to
UV light the outdoor environment will
become more dangerous one thing that
would also be true is that it would be
imperative not to give
at that selective signal in other words
to the extent that today it might be
very difficult to contract this outdoors
I would say that does not mean relax
outdoors I would say it means go
outdoors and be very vigilant about the
means of preventing it from jumping so
we don't give one of it a hint to give
one of these strains a hint about some
other way it could be transmitted right
so I mean I guess maybe just to just
fill it out a little bit I think on the
last live stream we showed a chart that
a doctor had put together so you know
estimating various risks from various
activities and if you've got three
activities that are possible go outside
but physically distance from people you
haven't been effectively in lockdown
within your home go outside and be in a
group of strangers versus go inside and
be in maybe let's take four you know
outside effectively alone or just with
those who you already shared pathogens
with outside and close proximity to
strangers inside alone but in a in a
place that maybe has had strangers in it
recently and inside and close quarters
inside and close quarters with strangers
is clearly at the moment given what this
virus is doing right now by far the way
that the virus is most likely to spread
then and outside without close proximity
strangers is by far the least likely way
to get the virus and in fact we see no
evidence that the virus is persisting in
any way outside if there are hemant
people around so you know outside
without being in close proximity to
other people it's always possible you
know the wind spreads would wind spreads
viral particles in strange ways but the
risk is diminished and they're low and
the health benefits in sight meal both
physical psychological mental health
benefits to being outside are huge and
that seems not just safe but like the
important thing to do whereas you know
outside in close proximity to a lot of
other people or inside but physically
distant saying say in a grocery store
both of those have
some risk to them and you know if you're
going to be outside close to the people
you should be wearing a mask if you're
going to be inside in close proximity to
other people or you know in a place
where there have been people you should
be not touching your face and washing
your hands frequently and making sure
that if you touch things you then don't
you know don't touch your face don't put
your hands up to your face so it's not
outside versus inside exactly it's
outside in combination with where could
the virus possibly have been and you
know it's not it's not living on plant
surfaces right it's it's not doing that
not to say that it couldn't start so
this is one of the things that's very
troubling about this movement to end the
lockdown and I won't wear a mask no
matter what and all of that is in some
sense I would be more sympathetic to the
contingent that wants to grow to greatly
reduce restrictions and what's possible
or eliminate them altogether if their
point was let's be hyper vigilant about
being careful rather than let's behave
like the virus isn't that serious
because at some level if we if some of
us begin behaving irresponsibly while
others of us behave responsibly those of
us who are behaving responsibly will
obviously suffer the cost of giving the
virus more landscape on which to
experiment and so at some level like it
or not we're all in this together and
that forces us to have a conversation
that yeah I agree it's very
uncomfortable but we really have to we
have to do it so we spent more than half
our time on this already maybe instead
of going in order here you want to jump
to the end not because we want to skip
everything in the middle because you've
already alluded to it several times and
basically the evidence continues to
mount as we have talked about in several
lab streams that being outside provides
protection against getting the virus
both because you're less likely to run
into it because if you do get it you're
more likely to have to be healthier
be more likely to resist serious illness
and you're also less likely to transmit
it to others being outside but this Zak
we want to put this up this wopo
Washington Post op edy makes many of
these points but it specifically it's
interesting and this is this is the era
we live in that it is based on a Twitter
thread by this person whose name I have
no idea how to pronounce I'm afraid muj
semuc i'm sure i'm butchering that where
that's not going the right place sorry
Zach if you want to pull that down so
she I believe it was a physician and a
scientist put together a really
impressive thread actually on Twitter
which you can get by linking to this
wopo article which we will put in the in
the notes about all of the evidence
that's been released so far suggesting
that actually being outside is is safer
and we should be making public policy
decisions based on that
unfortunately because you and I have
both been talking about this since
actually you know I started saying
things like this on social media before
we even start our first live stream that
yes we need to social distance and
really physical distance is probably the
better term but we should not nature
distance there is exactly no evidence
that nature Dismas saying is helpful and
in fact it seems to be harmful but there
are there is there is a failure of
nuance across the board now right and
what we're seeing is people who are
finding the lockdowns constraining feel
that they are evidence of an
authoritarian governing structure
looking for people with credentials who
are of like mind right so I don't know
Brett if this is where we want to go
here sure okay so Zak you want to put
this up we first were aware Tim Poole
who we have we've met we know we like we
did we both did a podcast with him a
long time ago put up a video on his
alternate site not his main
gasps site in which the title is
professor make strong case for ending
lockdown which is based on your bread
tweet which was based on what was a Joe
Rogan's conversation with a researcher
suggesting that vitamin D was helpful in
fighting the virus and your tweet was
just once again once again saying guess
what being outside is not the problem
those parts of the policy of the
lockdown policies need to change not
only not the problem but part of the
solution because of the vitamin D
connection if the vitamin D connection
holds then outdoor is actually curative
so I don't know what else you want to
say about this just that it's it's
unfortunate and alarming that someone
who has been in the past truth seeker
and a truth teller is using effectively
your credential to make a claim to
suggest that you are making a claim that
is opposite of what you are making that
you are not suggesting that ending
lockdown is the right move what you were
suggesting what both of us have been
suggesting for a long time is that
lockdown needs to be done smart and that
there is no way that any of these
policies ever should have included
keeping people out of nature areas so
long as they could use them in such a
way to keep them physically distanced
from other people yeah
it is important that we not do this we
have to be having a discussion in which
nuance is the the rule rather than the
exception and being shoved into some
known position
in order to get clicks or advance the
ball or something like that is a mistake
we need viral adjust to be sharing their
disagreements with each other about the
possible origin of this thing we need to
be discussing but what it means and we
need to be discussing what to do with
people being free to advance positions
that aren't mainstream without being
shoved into one of the mainstream
positions and you know never occurred to
me it even did not occur to me that I
was going to be understood to be
advocating an end to lock down right
because when it's but I mean it's been
fascinating in a grim sort of way to see
what some of the responses have been
that you know this you were on a you
were actually on a call when I saw this
so I tweeted it out first
asking Tim saying like we respect you
man we like you this is an error please
fix it we we believe you to be more
interested in truth that clicks
unfortunately it's now something like 24
hours later and it's not fixed and both
in response to my public objection and
to yours that just came a couple hours
later simply because you were you were
busy at the time we are both seen a lot
of pushback from people saying what's
your objection it's fine yeah this is so
you know listen to the video it's like
you know the title of the video and the
thumbprint are the thumbnail of the
video both say specifically are both
appear to be borrowing your credentials
using your authority which you know both
of us always try to hand our authority
away in the classroom say don't trust us
because we come here with PhD is trust
us beat you know ultimately come to
trust us because we have proven
ourselves trustworthy or seek
information elsewhere if you don't come
to trust us but continue to question
everything we say you know like like we
say all the time you questioned all
roles honor the good ones and work
against the bad ones this is a question
of lockdown never should have included
these rules and a number of people are
saying well see you're just talking
about using lock downs like no this is
not the argument lockdown shouldn't have
looked like this in the first place and
there are several aspects of lockdown
that aspect in in the vast majority of
places in the world seem to still be
necessary given continuingly increasing
rates of infection and hospitalization I
would point people also if they go look
at the tweet so that tweet got retweeted
and liked a bunch I think which which
one the one that him is invoking here so
Tim is referenced annoys Twitter of mine
sure if you can I get that but that
tweet was liked by a wide range now I
obviously can't look at ten thousand
likes but I can see the blue checkmark
likes and it appealed to people
across the political spectrum right from
people who are on the far left to people
who are on the far right it resonated
with people which tells me that this is
a perspective which is waiting to be
given proper voice and in any case to
have it shoved into one of the naive
perspectives either one of them either
you know keep the parks and beaches
closed that perspective or the end
lockdown now perspective both of those
are uninteresting and they're both wrong
yeah here it is what you say your quote
tweeting Joe Rogan who says vitamin D
may reduce the soft ability to cope at
19 associated lung injury based on a
stream that he did I gather on May 14th
you say it is insane that as the
evidence for vitamin D is protective
effect amounts and though it appears the
virus is very rarely transmitted
outdoors we continue to instruct people
to stay indoors where co2 is easily
transmitted and where they can't make
vitamin D and you know I read that again
now and I see ok if I'm trying if I'm
trying to steal man what I really
believe to be mostly bad faith takes on
the other side but I'm trying to steal
man it maybe you could read this as we
continue to instruct people to stay
indoors as yes we've been doing it but
we need to stop that and this is you
know this is the read that people have
been that people who don't seem to
understand the nuance here have been
taking you're suggesting is lock downs
well no you're not suggesting is lock
downs your suggests we're both
suggesting do lock downs right and get
rid of immediately all of the bad parts
of the policy yeah I mean the point is
lockdown sucks to the extent that we
need it for epidemiological reasons
let's make it as painless and healthy as
possible this is an obvious place that
we could make things better now I do
have one regret about my tweet which I
didn't even occur to me until people
started calling me out about it which is
the word instruct I don't believe that
we are actually instructing people to
stay indoors per se there are examples
of people who've been told to get out of
their yards and things like that but
those are going to be rare what we are
doing they're very common in some places
in England there is a lot of that okay
so what we are doing though
is we are keeping the places that people
might go out doors closed in many
locations and that is causing those who
do out go out doors to concentrate so
it's the same kind of mistake as between
the local trains and the Express trains
in cities and it is also not offering
people the kinds of opportunities
outdoors so at some level commerce is
dangerous in many regards there are
certain things that can be made safer
and there are certain things that are
necessary but commerce tends to
concentrate people inside of buildings
whereas going to the park going to the
beach you know taking a hike on a trail
those things appear to be safe and
healthy so in any case maybe we've said
enough enough about that can I go back
and correct one thing before people take
me to task ok I do not mean to imply
that coronaviruses have crossing over in
the same sense as mammals what they do
have is mechanisms for exploring design
space that are analogous ok so what we
were going to talk about in part
stemming from the original discussion of
Explorer modes today was why in this
particular environment censorship which
is always a problem maybe it you know is
particularly onerous now and I feel like
you sort of you did that you said right
now of all times we need access
everyone needs access to all the
information so that smart people
everywhere can sift through everything
that's going on and given you know you
said last time where are the biologists
who are who are disagreeing with the
party line in part we are beginning to
see censorship across all domains and so
it's becoming harder and harder for
people to find the information so let me
just we just had a few examples here
right we have this is now a while ago
actually almost a month ago on April
18th Susan Wojcicki who's the CEO CEO I
think of YouTube said on CNN's
interestingly named reliable sources
podcast that YouTube would be taking
down any videos that go against the
World Health Organization
recommendations or our quote medically
unsubstantiated
obviously the who has royally screwed up
in a number of places in the treatment
of this crisis and not to say I'm not
I'm not arguing that they haven't tried
to do their best or at least many of
them haven't tried to do their best but
the idea that the who is the arbiter of
not what it is the policy boat policy
should be happening but what information
is allowed to be spread to the public by
people who are interested in spreading
information is dangerous at best well it
also it goes back to something you said
I think on our last live stream which
was science is not set and forget and so
the idea that there is some Authority
that understands kovat 19 well enough to
offer advice that is so solid that it is
beyond disagreement is preposterous on
its face and to have the major platforms
playing with this kind of analytical
authoritarianism is beyond lethal who
the hell do they think they are that
they understand this so well that
they're gonna tell us what other
possibilities might turn out to be true
that is absolutely insane and you know
we all get it there's garbage
information out there there's there's
not a person connected to the Internet
who doesn't know that right you are not
the arbiter of where that border is this
is the same problem that we have faced
in science forever
there are a lot of cooks and among them
are people who see something ahead that
the rest of us don't yet you can't shut
down the garbage without shutting down
the people who know what's coming so
stop it yeah and we talked about this in
was it episode 11 choose your own black
mirror episode when we specifically were
doing a takedown of the kern county
doctors video there their analysis was
flawed across in so many ways that it
was really hard to to watch it without
without taking pages and pages of notes
about where they got things wrong but as
as we talked about at length in that
episode as i was in the middle of
watching it i had taken a break for us
to have dinner youtube took it down and
then they took down another one
and ended up on bit sheet words findable
to this day as it should be right like
as it needs to be so these you know that
was another example of you know
certainly much of what they were saying
was medically unsubstantiated and I
would argue not not going to be not
going to end up being appropriate for
the evidence but that doesn't mean that
we shouldn't have access to it similarly
we've got now the planned emic
documentary which we spoke a little bit
about last time and the evidence against
that but that's been taken down and you
know we are now talking about examples
of videos that we think are so deeply
flawed that yes some people will take
away wrong and wrong headed ideas from
them but they need to be out there so
we've got the current County doctors
we've got the planned emic documentary
we also now just in the last day or two
I've been hearing a lot about this
Delores Cahill don't know if I'm
pronouncing her name right this
physician I think out of Great Britain
somewhere who much like those earlier
videos seems to be not hypothesis driven
not even data driven but conclusion
driven she's got some conclusion she's
got frankly some political motive that
she's shooting for and and it she
doesn't appear to be an honest broker
but that doesn't mean that we shouldn't
be able to see what she has to say
so just because this is this question
about her has come at us a lot in the
last day I want to just put up a
screenshot of this video that you can
put out now Zak which and again we'll
put the URL for the bit sheet video here
she is this is her rendering of the
difference between corona and Ebola not
to indicate the corona is no problem at
all and there are problems in almost
every cell you know age range most
effected for corona over 80 well if you
ask someone in late January that was
what we thought but I don't think anyone
thinks that's true now age range not
affected children nope wrong our masks
effective to stop spread of infection no
real
you know so and then maybe worst of all
is up at the top and this is just
mathematical sleight of hand with regard
to the death rate the denominator that
she uses for Ebola is out of 10,000 and
the denominator that she chooses for
Corona is out of 1000 which makes the
overall numbers seem like they're way
way WAY lower for corona virus than for
Ebola and that right there tells me even
even if she was legitimately confused
about the contents of every other cell
anyone with college-level mathematics or
I would hope middle school level
mathematics but anyone who is licensed
as a scientist who willingly puts
numbers up that switches the
denominators and which therefore changes
the read on what the death rate is is
not up to any good still this should be
up this should be available and if I
said it's on bit shoot and has
presumably been you know thrown out of
YouTube is again more of the problem
yeah it's a it's a terrible problem I I
would suggest for people trying to
figure out how you deal with questions
like this without getting pushed into
one of these buzz saws or another there
are certain hallmarks that are going to
be important one when people make an
error did they come back and correct it
do they tell you I made an error and
here's what it was and here's the truth
or do they leave it up are people prone
to an embrace every conspiracy theory or
are they selectively do they talk in
terms of hypotheses and are they very
selective about the ones that they give
credence to I would just point out that
no matter what your belief system is it
ought to be true that most conspiracy
hypotheses are false so if most of them
are false then your tendency to reject
them ought to be high and if it isn't
that says that your quality control
isn't very good but what you have here
is a case in which we are simultaneously
pointing out errors in other people's
work and advocating that that work
remain available and this has got to be
where the platforms
land otherwise they're gonna create a
nightmare and they already are that's
right and just one more thing on this
before we're gonna try to get to two
more topics before you know a few
minutes is up here but the preprint
servers which have before this global
pandemic been a place for people to put
papers in advance of them being usually
printed as opposed to accept it but
maybe even just as they have I don't
actually know what the various rules
have been for when papers end up in pre
print service but at the moment these
have been through the clearing houses
for anything that you've got that you
that is relevant to the modern moment
with regard to coronavirus if you've
done a piece of experimental research or
a review paper you can put it up and
your show this for a moment sac nature
publishes now a week ago how swamped
preprint servers are blocking bad
coronavirus research now that word
swamped suggests that they just can't
handle it and that's of course editorial
against sleight of hand by Nature when
actually what the preprint servers are
trying to do is cover their asses and
get rid of some of the maybe less savory
or less I don't even know what
politically correct medically correct
you know whatever it is results that
they're not liking so even the preprint
servers now are doing sort of behind the
scenes edit on what it is that we can
see yeah it's part of what Eric calls
the distributed idea suppression complex
the disk right when it maintains the
gated institutional narrative and so
here nature which is like the you know
one of the pillars of the gated
institutional narrative is trying to
shut down a mechanism through which
other people are exploring ideas that
nature doesn't want to touch hello I
mean nature's not shutting it down
nature's it's just nature's headline
that centers broadcasting as this and it
is characterizing it as swamped servers
which I would point out is an echo we
have peer-review in part because on
paper there was some need to sort
quality from non quality because there's
a limit of how much paper and ink there
is
expensive stuff that wasn't the entire
reason but that's part of the reason in
a world of electronic journals this is
no longer necessary
and anyway nature is now trying to
characterize the preprint servers as
having limited space and that's the
reason they need to do this which is of
course nonsense okay I think we have to
choose between these either talking
about the theater Theodore Roosevelt
aircraft carrier or the T cells found in
Kovac 19 patients bode well for long
term immunity which which are they
should we go they are unfortunately
connected so let's try to do it quickly
so we have all I could find at the last
minute here is an NPR story suggesting
that what we've seen we've seen
indications a few places that the
Theodore Roosevelt aircraft carrier
which we've talked about earlier
livestreams and had several people who
had tested positive I don't remember
what the number was for as far more than
five but five servicemen who had
previously tested positive had them
tested negative and it's been many weeks
I think have tested positive again
tested positive after testing negative
to a very high standard I think there's
something over a thousand cases and Zak
you do have the Navy's I think the Navy
Times report on this can you put that up
okay so this is a very scary possibility
and we've alluded to it before we don't
know if it's true or not you know of
course one of one of one of the
implications of this could be actually
those negative tests that the servicemen
got in the interim were wrong and they
were positive the whole time but if true
it means that the possibility of
reinfection exists which is to say that
having had at least one strain of sorry
Scobie - does not protect you against
possibly other strains and of course no
one is talking about the distinction
between strains we should spend some
time on that in the future or
re-emergence sort of in the style isn't
exactly yet but I've you know from for
me the model I have in my head is vivax
malaria that tends to hide out in the
liver not be detectable by malaria tests
while it's hiding out and and the person
who's carrying it is asymptomatic but
when it comes out of the liver the
person becomes symptomatic and
when in you know because malaria is
vectored if a mosquito bites you then
then you can transmit to other people so
reemergence who knows where it's hiding
if that's the case or reinfection yeah
both of these are possible
interpretations as you point out it
could also be erroneous but this is a
very frightening possibility and those
who are pushing a wreckless I don't want
to say agenda but are proposing a
removal of lockdown and basically
letting the virus run its course are
creating a much greater danger if either
one of these things is true if either
there's no immunity long term immunity
generated by contracting Tsarskoe v2 or
it hides out in some tissue and RIA
merges periodically both of these would
be very bad outcomes okay so the second
thing that the final thing that we
wanted to talk about before taking a
break is this science report so this is
again a reporting of about some other
research that has been done Zack if you
would show it please T cells found in
Koba 19 patients bode well and quotes
for long-term immunity and this and this
is gonna require a little bit of
immunology to parse and we also have the
the original papers that this paper is
citing I don't know how much we want to
spend on this well I think that this
story actually buried the lede so I
don't
maybe I'm just off here but I don't
think it's very surprising at all that T
cells that react to SARS co2 are found
in people who have had these infections
that would be absolutely expected that
doesn't certainly at least within a few
months of home been infected right she's
the longest possible moment that people
could have been infected with this virus
at this point exactly so it's hard to
imagine that this would unfold without
t-cell involvement and so that there
would be some selective reactivity by
these T cells
the more important thing was that it
appears exact I need my computer that no
just chill some people appear to have
reactivity who have never had SARS cove
- now that could be one of a number of
things it could be that they have had it
and the tests are incorrect which is a
possibility we should spend time on at
some point but it is also possible that
the reason that some people who've never
contracted this virus do already have T
cells that react circulating in their
systems is exposure to prior
coronaviruses especially the for
circulating cold viruses so there are
four corona viruses that circulate
people get them regularly these are
seasonal cold viruses and so to the
extent that these are relatives an
immune system that has seen these cold
viruses then reacts with some
specificity to Sarah's Cove - so let's
just put this up this is one of the
papers that the science news report is
responding to and I think that that is
exactly the interesting possibility
there especially in light of the
unfortunate meme that is now beginning
to circulate that corona viruses do
great damage to humans but then they
disappear right because SARS one seems
to have disappeared and MERS seems to
have disappeared well there are these
four other circulating corona viruses
probably many more than that but four
named circulating corona viruses that
produce the common cold that have been
circulating for years they didn't
disappear they're not just disappearing
so is there something different about
this one compared to SARS one and MERS
versus the other corona viruses that are
circulating and widespread and
effectively endemic in the human
population presumably there is something
different but the idea that we are
certain that this one is more like more
likely to be like SARS one and MERS then
like the higher number of endemic
circulating current of viruses is seems
like a very dangerous position
well I think this actually brings us
back full circle because one of the
reasons that one might expect this to
behave more like the common cold
coronaviruses and less like the Tsar's
and MERS example that we have is that
this one may have been turbocharged by
human tinkering presumably with good
intent but human tinkering that turned
this into something that spreads like
wildfire and so in some sense the reason
that SARS and MERS died out is they were
not particularly well adapted to leap
between people that's obviously not what
we're dealing here and to the extent
that we might be dealing with a virus
that has been induced to experiment at a
high rate and therefore will quickly
learn how to defeat measures that we
deploy we may be in much more serious
trouble and we should not take SARS and
Marrissa as the expectation we certainly
don't know enough to imagine that that's
the trajectory we're going to face here
that's right all right have we covered
it and is it time to take a break and
then return with a new link you will
find it in the description to this live
stream there will be a new link we'll be
back in about 15 minutes to answer two
Twitter questions and as many super chat
questions as we can get - all right
we're looking forward to it see you soon
you